weak pointers the pointers for those of
you who are just not quite strong enough
to use proper
pointers recently I made a video as part
of my code review series talking about
why this code failed this like test or
application that the person submitted it
for and I specifically mentioned that a
potential Improvement in one area would
have been to use weak pointers instead
of just raw pointers okay so yeah the
the way that these observers get
registered here is they get the raw
pointer from an actual shed pointer so
yes I'm right in the sense that they are
kind of trying to use this if I can find
it they are trying to use this like a
weak pointer but the problem is it's not
that safe because you just have a
pointer you've got a memory address to
something that is like you're not owning
it which means it could get deleted and
you might still have it and if you try
and access it like you're accessing
freed memory and that would cause a
crash so the way to go here is to look
up something called a weak pointer STD
weak pointer so I thought today we would
just kind of sit down have a bit of a
discussion as to what weak pointers are
when it might be a good idea to use them
and why so first of all what is a weak
pointer when I say weak pointer I'm
specifically talking about SD weak
pointer it's a class included in the C++
standard library and it's specifically
designed to be used with shared pointers
let me show you how it works and what it
does a shared pointer is a wrapper
around a raw pointer in this case of a
heap allocated object that is called
object that's the type we're dealing
with here it's a wrapper around that raw
pointer that would otherwise be written
like this and the purpose of it is to
kind of automate the life lifetime
management of it so in the simplest
scenario if we just look at this exact
code that we have here very very simple
the difference between these two and why
we kind of like Shar pointer is that
this code will result in this object
instance being deleted automatically at
the end of this scope whereas with
object two we would manually have to
call delete now technically unique
pointer would obviously do the same
thing if we did SCD make unique here
instead of make shared and this was a
unique pointer it would also be deleted
at the end of the scope but the real
magic of shared points is that we can
share it we can have multiple places
inside our program that contain these
references to that object and when all
of them are gone when all of them are
out of scope and the actual shared
pointer itself gets destroyed as long as
they're all gone there's none left at
that point our underlying object
instance gets deleted you can't do that
with a unique pointer obviously because
there can only really be one copy of
that and that's it it's fantastic for
like Scopes but if you have an object
that you want to share around using
colle use outside of like one given
function or class instance then this
reference counting system which simply
just maintains a count of how many
shared pointer references there are to a
given object instance works really well
and so for example if I introduce this
manager structure over here which as you
can see holds an object as a Shar
pointer I can share this object that I
made here in this scope with this other
system that is in its own scope might
have its own lifetime might do whatever
with it and I know that unless unless
both of these independently die I'm not
going to lose that underlying object
instance so this is just a little bit of
a recap and the reason why I'm going
through this is because these we kind of
just call these references because this
is a reference counting system these
shared pointers but a more specific term
for these kinds of references is
something called a strong reference and
the reason why this is called a strong
reference is because it's basically it's
not just an reference to this object
that allows us to use it it's a
reference that is strong enough to
actually keep keep the object alive
meaning that as long as I keep that
reference alive I'm actually preventing
that underlying object instance from
dying picture that the power to prevent
something from dying G where can I learn
this power not from a Jedi I'll tell you
where you can learn that power you can
learn that power with brilliant.org
30-day free trial for those of you who
don't know brilliant.org is an amazing
website filled with lots and lots of
really high quality courses on various
stem topics and thanks to their 30-day
free trial you can explore all of these
courses for free and see if you like
them if you're just getting into
programming then I highly recommend you
take a look at brilliant's excellent
beginner computer science courses
they're really going to make sure that
you have the right frame of mind and
teach you how to think like a programmer
and honestly it's really easy to just
pick it up and get learning because all
of Brilliance courses are extremely
visual engaging and interactive instead
of just sitting back and watching videos
and zoning out you'll actually have to
interact with the teaching material
they'll get you to actually drag things
around build these kind of flow graphs
see visually how everything kind of fits
together and and works which is
fantastic and then of course everybody's
favorite subject math brilliant has some
of the best math courses I've honestly
ever seen and the reason why is because
I just think math is such a beautiful
topic to teach visually it really
benefits from like these widgets that
you can drag around especially for the
more advanced topics like calculus and
getting quizzed every step of the way to
make sure that you're actually learning
and retaining this information really
makes for a very powerful learning
experience and as I mentioned 30-day
free trial just go to br/ theurn link
will be in description below try it out
for yourselves see if you like it and if
you do go on to like it Brant have been
nice enough to offer 20% off an annual
premium subscription using that link in
the description below huge thank you to
brilliant as always for sponsoring this
video so back to preventing things from
dying shared pointers strong references
they will keep things alive they're also
called an owning reference that
basically just means that they I guess
take ownership of an object ownership
they they still share ownership it's not
like they are the sole owner but in this
case by sharing this object with the
manager I'm now saying that this
underlying instance won't die until
manager also is okay with it Dying by I
guess it dying itself lots of dying
going on welcome to C++ so then what do
people usually do if they don't want
this ownership kind of owning strong
reference what if I just want to give
manager access to this object but I'm
cool if it dies like it's fine for it to
die I don't want to be the one stopping
it from dying it's a little too close of
a relationship with this object here I
just want to be chill I just want to be
like you die it's cool man but if you're
alive I might use you so one way to do
this is to Simply drop this shared
pointer aspect we could just go back to
this being a raw pointer in that case
we'd have to change this API to
basically be do get like that so on the
actual shed pointer itself not the
object obviously the shed pointer we're
calling the get function which just
Returns the raw pointer you can see it
over here right this now means that if
this object does in fact die what does
manager have just a point Po and what is
that just an integer just a memory
address so obviously this can't do
anything to keep that object from dying
it's going to die or it's not going to
die all we are holding is basically like
some kind of number which just says
where is it in memory now hopefully for
a lot of you this already seems like a
little bit of a problem because if we
are simply holding this number in memory
how do we know if it's safe to use it or
not because what happens if it has in
fact been deleted we've lost it he's
dead gym what happens if we try and use
it in that case an explosion will happen
and the thing is the worst part about
this is you really can't do anything to
actually check that can you because if
you could do something like that well
that would be cool but that only works
if something sets this to null right if
I set this to something like this and
actually let's make this a little bit
more complicated let's maybe put manager
up here so it doesn't die and then what
I'm going to do is put this into a scope
let's get rid of this as well so if I
take a look at this now and just to make
this even more explicit let's add a
Destructor where we'll print deleted
object if I run this program then you
can see the problem I've deleted the
object first and then what am I doing
I'm able to access that pointer and
obviously all we're doing here is we're
actually printing the value of the
pointer we're not accessing the memory
at that memory address we're just simply
printing the memory address which is
obviously fine to do in any case but you
can see that it still looks like a valid
memory address which means that this
code will run fine the only way in this
case to get around that would be if we
explicitly after deleting it actually
set that to null but like we don't even
know if we're going to delete it here do
we we have no idea because something
else might also have a Shar pointer of
that object because we can share it
around so we've kind of created this
like impossible situation here where we
have no way of ever knowing when that
shed pointer is completely gone deleted
just disappeared and instead we're left
with a situation where we have a raw
pointer that is always going to have a
seemingly valid memory address that is
just really a time bomb waiting to just
crash and destroy our program so what
can we do instead of using a raw pointer
here since clearly that's not going to
work out too well that is where weak
pointers come in they are you can think
of them as shared pointers cuz I want to
share stuff with you but I don't want
you to own it so I'm not creating a
strong reference here to an object I'm
creating a weak reference they're really
quite powerful like from a kind of
semantics point of view and they're
super easy to use so if we transform
this into using wak pointers instead of
a raw pointer here we would simply have
SD weak pointer the type obviously and
can get rid of this over here instead of
ob. getet we simply assign this to the
shared pointer itself because weak
pointer has a Constructor that takes in
a shared pointer and then the last piece
of the puzzle here is how do I do my
little safety check well there's a
couple ways the best way to probably
rewrite this specific code is to write
something like Auto obge equals ob.
loock and then over here you can just
you know use your object as normal if
that succeeds otherwise you cannot so
what actually happens over here because
I've written Auto here which can be a
little bit hiding what's actually going
on what happens when we call this lock
function is you can see it actually
returns a shed pointer of that object so
we're kind of converting this weak
pointer back into a shared pointer why
because if we need to use the object
suddenly we do want a strong reference
don't we because if we don't maintain a
strong reference then a lot can actually
change between this line of code and
this line of code right if we just had
for example a I don't know like an
object pointer like this then something
in between these two lines could
actually delete the underlying object
why well because multi-threading exists
right some other thread might be the
last thing actually holding on to a shed
pointer to that strong reference it
might release it everything looked good
at line 15 line 17 when we try and use
it suddenly oh actually sorry it's not
valid anymore so what this does instead
is it has a shared pointer it gives us a
Shar pointer of that weak pointer object
and now for this entire scope because
we've got a Shar pointer now it will
keep this object alive even if nothing
else does so that of course is really
really important and of course since
lock gives us a shared pointer that is
obviously capable of dying and thus
unlocking the object we don't have to
like manually call unlock or anything
like that all it does is it gives us a
strong reference that we can do whatever
with for whatever kind of duration we
need to now if you just want to check
though whether or not it's valid you can
instead call the expired function and
that will just basically tell you
whether or not that object has been
deleted so if you don't necessarily need
to use it but you just want to check to
see if it's still alive you can and then
finally this other thing that I like is
there's a function here called use count
and that's kind of cool because what
that does is it actually gives you the
reference count so you can see in how
many places in your program are you
actually holding a strong reference to
this object so in this case because
we're only have one shared pointer over
here if we call this function before
that shared pointer actually dies I'd
expect it to say one in fact we can try
that by calling this function multiple
times and then you can see we have one
first then deleted object and then zero
so I guess technically if you wanted to
you could also write something like that
as well so hopefully that sheds a little
bit of light as to what weak pointers
are and where it's just a really good
convenient idea to use them obviously
there is some overhead added to this
system versus just using raw pointers so
it's not necessarily a situation where
you should go through and replace every
single raw pointer you have that's made
from like a shed pointer or something
and just replace it with a weak pointer
but the thing is it's one of those like
overheads that's like well what about
using smart pointers in the first place
like unique pointer does that have a bit
of overhead I mean unique pointer really
doesn't but like Shar pointer has a bit
of overhead so should I not use shared
pointers should I not use reference
counting well it's just one of those
situations where there's no other choice
in some cases than to use say reference
counting or weak pointers and in my
opinion in most cases the overhead is so
negligible that I would probably just
use weak pointers one use case that I
can think of where like literally it's
mandatory to use them otherwise it won't
work is when you have like a cyclical
dependency so if you have object a
having a sharpoint at object B and
object B having a sharpoint at object a
they will never die because there's
always going to be something holding
that object so like for example take a
look at this program we have a struct
called A and A structor called B they
have shared pointers pointing to each
other here we have a andb you can see
they're kind of wired up like this if I
run this program check this out there's
nothing being destroyed we create these
objects but where at the end of the
scope they don't get destroyed but if we
go over here to this one for example
example and we make B have a weak
pointer of a instead of a strong pointer
then suddenly they're both destroyed at
the end of the scope so this is an
example in which maybe we want both
objects to have like a reference to each
other which again is perfectly valid we
might need to do work you know they
might need to do work together but you
have to be careful with strong
references in this case and now finally
let's take a look at that kind of real
world example that we had from the code
review that I did in the last video that
I talked about where specifically you
can see we had like this input Handler
which allowed us to register an observer
and you can see takes in a raw pointer
and where does that come from that comes
from you know game switch state for
example where it actually takes current
state which is a shared pointer and
calls do get on it to get the r pointer
and then that gets put into like
register Observer for example so how can
we rewrite the systems use weak pointers
instead and thus not just blindly you
know like iterate through all these
observers as role pointers not knowing
if they're still there or not well over
here inside the input Handler we have a
vector and you can see the vector has
raw pointers so instead we can just
change that to be a weak pointer like
this and then all of these same exact
scenario you can just pass these in by
value like that it's totally okay to
just copy weak pointer instances like
this let me just go to these definitions
and make sure that I've also got them
set up like this and then when iterating
through this this is where we have the
option to actually do that safety
checking that I was talking about so to
simp simplify this we could just call
this Auto Observer like that and then
before using it we could lock it right
so maybe I'll do something like OBS like
that equals observer. loock and then if
that succeeds I could go ahead and
actually call on Mouse left click on
that Observer otherwise if it isn't
valid anymore it might make sense to
just remove it as an observer so that I
don't have to keep iterating through it
obviously because it's been deleted so
in that case I might just want to call
remove Observer with that specific
Observer now if you really wanted to
make sure this code was a bit more solid
as well obviously it's possible to
register an observer that is an invalid
week pointer in the first place it might
just be null in that case you you'll
just end up removing it I guess
instantly it should probably be okay but
that might be worth checking if you care
and then over here we have the same kind
of situation but for a quit event again
I would probably just make this Auto
Observer and then if the Locking
succeeds I can call that function and
that's it so that would be like the
safer way I guess to deal with these
observers if you didn't want to
necessarily risk I guess then dying
outside of this since we don't actually
hold strong references to them inside
this class to those of you watching
would you change the code to what I
changed it to or would you keep it as is
with the raw pointers let me know why in
the comments section below but otherwise
I hope you guys enjoy this video on weak
pointers let me know what your thoughts
are in general as well with using them
like how often do you actually use weak
pointers how often do you see other
people use weak pointers and are you for
them are you against them do you think
they over complicate things I don't
personally think it's necessarily a
debate of whether or not AR they useful
of course they're useful it's more about
like how much do you actually use them
because I mean inside Hazel for example
we don't actually use share pointers we
have our own reference counting system
that's probably a topic for another
video and with that custom reference
counting system in Hazel weak pointers
do exist and to be honest they're super
useful for things like debugging a lot
of the times you might want to kind of
almost have a view into something
because you just want to keep track of
it so that you can like display it in
the UI as like some list of like a
references you have of like all images
for example inside Vulcan but then
because you're kind of just an observer
of that debug information that you care
about you obviously don't want to keep
it alive you just want to have it around
if it's valid if it's not it's cool but
if it's valid let me keep that around so
that I can then pull stuff from it if I
need to so for situations like that I
find that it's super useful anyway thank
you guys for watching I will see you
next time goodbye